I think perhaps the thing that most surprised
아마도 제가 가장 놀랐던 점은
me is the extent to which I feel
제가 느끼기에 그 정도가
like the AI economy
AI 경제가
stabilized. We have like the model layer companies
안정화됐다는 점입니다. 모델 계층 회사들이 있고
and the application layer companies and the
애플리케이션 계층 회사들도 있고
infrastructure layer companies. It seems like everyone is
인프라 계층 회사들도 있습니다. 모두가
going to make a lot of money and
큰돈을 벌 것 같고
there's kind of like a relative playbook for
AI 네이티브 회사를
how to build an AI native company on
모델 위에서 어떻게 만들지에 대한
top of the models.
어느 정도의 플레이북도 생긴 것 같습니다.
Many episodes ago we talked about how it
몇 에피소드 전 저희가
was felt easier than ever to peer and
스타트업 아이디어를 찾아보는 일이 그 어느 때보다
find a startup idea
쉽게 느껴진다고 이야기한 적이 있습니다.
because if you could just survive, if you
왜냐하면 그저 버티기만 할 수 있다면, 그리고
just wait a few months, there was likely
몇 달만 기다리면, 아마
going to be
곧
some like big announcement that would completely make
완전히 새로운 아이디어들을 가능하게 만드는
a new set of ideas possible. And so
큰 발표가 나올 가능성이 높기 때문이었습니다. 그래서
like
결국
finding ideas is sort of returning to sort
아이디어를 찾는 일이 다시
of normal levels of difficulty.
정상적인 난이도 수준으로 돌아가고 있는 것 같습니다.
Welcome back to another episode of The Light
The Light Cone의 또 다른 에피소드에 다시 오신 것을 환영합니다.
Cone. Today we're talking about the most surprising
오늘은 2025년에 저희가 본 것들 중
things that we saw this year in 2025.
가장 놀라웠던 것들에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
Diana, you found a pretty crazy one. It's
Diana, 정말 놀라운 걸 하나 찾으셨더군요. 이건
sort of a changing
일종의
of the guard almost in who is the
YC 배치에서 선호되는 LLM이 누군지에 대해
preferred LLM at YC during the YC batch.
거의 판도가 바뀐 것 같은 이야기입니다.
Yes. In fact, we just wrapped up the
네. 사실 저희가 방금
winter 26 selection cycle for companies. And one
기업들을 대상으로 한 Winter 26 선발 사이클을 마무리했습니다. 그리고
of the
그 과정에서
questions we asked to all the founders that
YC에 지원하는 모든 창업자분들께
apply to YC is what is your tech
기술 스택이 무엇인지와
stack and model of choice?
선호하는 모델이 무엇인지 질문합니다.
And one of the shocking things is that
그런데 충격적인 점 중 하나는
for the longest time, OpenAI was the clear
아주 오랫동안 OpenAI가
winner
명확한 1위였고
for all of last year, last couple of
작년 내내와 최근 몇 개의 배치 동안
batches, though that number has been coming down.
그 비중이 내려오고 있었다는 점입니다.
And shockingly, in this batch, the number one
그런데 놀랍게도 이번 배치에서 1위
API is actually Anthropic. It came out a
API는 실제로 Anthropic이었습니다. 약간
bit more than
OpenAI보다 더 높게 나왔는데
OpenAI, which who would have thought? I think
누가 이런 걸 예상했겠습니까? 저희가
when we started this podcast series back then,
이 팟캐스트 시리즈를 시작했을 때만 해도
OpenAI was like 90 plus percent. And now,
OpenAI가 90% 이상이었는데, 지금은
Anthropic, who would have thought?
Anthropic이라니, 누가 생각했겠습니까?
Yeah. And you know, they'd been hovering around
네. 그리고 아시다시피 Anthropic은
like 20, 25% for most of like
2024년 대부분과 2025년 초까지는
2024 and early 2025. And then
대략 20~25% 정도에서 머물렀습니다. 그런데
only even in the last three to six
정말 최근 3~6개월 사이에
months, did this sort of changing of the
이런 세대교체가
guard actually happen?
실제로 일어났습니다.
They had this hockey stick with the with
성장이 하키스틱처럼 급격히 치솟아
the growth are over 52%.
52%를 넘겼습니다.
Why do you think that is?
왜 그렇다고 생각하십니까?
I think there's a couple of things in
기술 스택 선택 측면에서
terms of the tech stack selection. I think
몇 가지 이유가 있다고 생각합니다. 올해 저희가 본 것처럼
as we've seen this year,
올해는
there's been a lot of wins in terms
바이브 코딩 도구들이 많이 성공했고
of vibe coding tools that are getting built
여기저기에서 계속 만들어지고 있습니다. 그리고
out out there. And
코딩 에이전트 같은 카테고리가 워낙 많아서
coding agents are so many categories that this
결국 이 분야가 더 큰 문제 영역이 되었고
ended up being a bigger problem space that
실제로 큰 가치를 만들어내고 있습니다. 그리고
actually is
알고 보니
creating a lot of value. And it turns
그 일을 가장 잘하는 모델이
out the model that performs the best at
결국
it is actually
실제로는
models from Anthropic. And I think that's not
Anthropic의 모델들입니다. 그리고 저는 그게
by accident. I think from hearing the conversation
우연이 아니라고 생각합니다. 얼마 전
we had with Tom Brown, not too long
Tom Brown과 나눴던 대화를 떠올려 보면
ago, he came and spoke is that was
그가 와서 말했듯이, 그것이
one of their internal evals.
그들의 내부 평가 중 하나였다고 합니다.
They, on purpose, made them their North Star.
그들은 의도적으로 그것을 자신들의 노스스타로 삼았습니다.
And you can see it in the model
그리고 그 결과가 모델에 그대로 드러납니다.
taste as a result of
그래서 모델 선택에서도 그런 성향이 나타납니다.
what's the best choice of model for a
제품을 만드는 많은 창업자들에게 어떤 모델이
lot of founders building products is Anthropic.
가장 좋은 선택인지 보면, Anthropic입니다.
The vast majority of the use cases people
다만 사람들이 사용하는 유스케이스의 대다수는
are using it for, though, is not coding.
코딩이 아닙니다.
So I wonder if there's
그래서 혹시
like a bleed through effect, where people are
일종의 스필오버 효과가 있어서 사람들이
using Claude for their personal coding. And then
개인 코딩에 Claude를 쓰고, 그러다
as a result, they're more likely to choose
그 결과로
it for their application, even if their application
애플리케이션에서도 그 모델을 선택할 가능성이 커지는
is
것 아닐까 하는데요,
not doing coding at all.
애플리케이션이 코딩을 전혀 하지 않더라도 말입니다.
Because you'd be very familiar with like the
왜냐하면 그러면
personality of Claude Opus or whatever they're
Claude Opus 같은 모델의 성격에, 또는
choosing. Sonnet, I suppose.
자신이 쓰는 모델에 매우 익숙해지기 때문입니다. 아마 Sonnet이겠지요.
How about Gemini? How's Gemini doing in those
Gemini는 어떤가요? 그런 순위에서 Gemini는
rankings?
어떻게 되고 있습니까?
Gemini has also pretty much has been climbing
Gemini도 거의 계속해서
up pretty, pretty high. I think last year
꽤 높은 순위까지 올라왔습니다. 작년에는
was
아마
probably single digit percent or even like two,
한 자릿수 퍼센트였거나 2%,
three percent. And now for winter 26, it's
3% 정도였을 텐데, 이제 Winter 26에서는
about
대략
23 percent. And we've personally been using also
23%입니다. 저희도 개인적으로
a lot of Gemini 3.0 and we've
Gemini 3.0을 많이 써 왔고
been impressed with
정말
the quality of it. I think it's really,
품질이 인상적이었습니다. 정말,
really working.
정말 잘 작동합니다.
I mean, they have all different personalities, don't
그러니까, 모델마다 성격이 다 다르지 않습니까?
they?
그렇지요?
That too.
맞습니다.
Yeah.
네.
It's kind of the classic where OpenAI sort
전형적인 비유로 OpenAI는
of has the black cat energy. And almost
좀 검은 고양이 같은 에너지가 있고, 거의
like
반면
Anthropic is kind of more the happy-go
Anthropic은 좀 더 낙천적이고
-lucky, a bit more very helpful golden retriever.
아주 친절한 골든리트리버에 가깝습니다.
At least
적어도
that's what I feel when I talk to
제가 그들과 이야기할 때는 그렇게
them.
느껴집니다.
And how about Gemini?
그럼 Gemini는 어떻습니까?
It's kind of like in between.
그 중간쯤인 것 같습니다.
Harj, you prefer Gemini, actually.
Harj, 사실 Gemini를 더 선호하시잖아요.
Yeah, I've switched to Gemini this year as
네, 저는 올해 Gemini로
my just go-to model. I think even
기본으로 쓰는 모델을 바꿨습니다. 심지어
before 2.5 Pro came
2.5 Pro가 나오기
out and just seemed better at reasoning for
전부터도 제게는 추론이 더 잘되는 것처럼
me, it was just like the increasingly I
느껴졌고, 저는 점점 더
replaced my
제
Google searches with Gemini. And I just sort
Google 검색을 Gemini로 대체했습니다. 그리고 저는
of trusted that Google's, I think like the
구글의, 그러니까
groundings
Grounding
API and its ability to actually like use
API와 실제로
the Google index to give you like real
구글 인덱스를 활용해
-time information
실시간 정보를
correctly. I just found it was better than,
정확히 제공하는 능력을 신뢰했습니다. 개인적으로는
personally I found it was better than all
그런 용도에서는
the
다른
other tools for that. And it was better
도구들보다 더 낫다고 느꼈습니다. 그리고
than Perplexity on it too. Like Perplexity would
그 부분에서는 Perplexity보다도 나았습니다. Perplexity는
be
대체로
fast, but not always accurate. And Gemini was
빠르지만 항상 정확하진 않았습니다. 반면 Gemini는
not quite as fast as Perplexity, but it
Perplexity만큼 빠르진 않았지만
was always
항상
pretty accurate if I asked it about something
제가 무언가를 물어보면 대체로 꽤 정확했고
that happened today, for example.
예를 들어 오늘 일어난 일도 그랬습니다.
Even if you use Gemini as the reasoning
Perplexity에서 추론 엔진으로 Gemini를
engine in Perplexity?
쓰더라도 그렇습니까?
I have not done that.
저는 그렇게 해본 적이 없습니다.
Interesting. Yeah. So it's hard to know like
흥미롭네요. 네, 그래서
how much of it is the tooling and
얼마나 툴링 덕분인지,
how much of it is
얼마나
like the base LLM.
기본 LLM 덕분인지는 알기 어렵습니다.
That's fair.
그 말도 맞습니다.
Yeah. I mean, what are your guys' tools
네. 그러면 여러분은 어떤 도구를
of choice? I haven't switched off of ChatGPT.
주로 쓰십니까? 저는 아직 ChatGPT에서 갈아타지 않았습니다.
I mean,
그러니까요,
I find the memory very sticky. It knows
메모리가 정말 강하게 남아 있어서요. 저를
me, it knows my personality, it knows the
알고, 제 성격도 알고, 제가
things that
생각하는
I think about. And so I'll use Perplexity
것들까지 압니다. 그래서 저는 Perplexity를
for fast web searches or things that I
빠른 웹 검색이나 제가
know is like
명확히
a research task because I think ChatGPT is
리서치 과제라고 아는 일에는 쓰는데, ChatGPT는
still like a little bit of a step
여전히 약간 한 걸음
behind for searching
뒤처진다고 생각합니다,
the web. I don't know. I think memory
웹 검색에서는요. 모르겠습니다만, 메모리가
is turning into an actual moat for like
사실상
that consumer experience.
그런 소비자 경험의 진짜 해자가 되고 있다고 봅니다.
And I don't expect Gemini to ever have
그리고 Gemini가 결코
the personality that I would expect from ChatGPT.
ChatGPT에서 기대하는 그런 성격을 갖게 될 것 같지는 않습니다.
It just feels like a different like entity,
그냥 다른 존재처럼 느껴집니다,
you know?
아시겠지요?
The thing I'm still surprised about is why
제가 여전히 놀라는 것은 왜
there just aren't more consumer apps around like
우리가 하는 온갖 일을 둘러싼
all the
소비자
various things we do. Like if I think
앱이 더 많지 않은가 하는 점입니다. 예를 들어
back, one of the big changes for me
돌이켜보면, 올해 제게 큰 변화 중 하나는
this year is just the amount of
그저
prompting and context engineering I do for like
제 삶을 위해 하는 프롬프팅과 컨텍스트 엔지니어링이
my life. Like we bought a house recently
얼마나 많아졌는가입니다. 예를 들어 최근 집을 샀는데
and like
그 과정에서
the whole thing, like I just had like
전체 과정 내내 저는 그냥
a really long running ChatGPT conversation stuffing it
아주 오래 이어진 ChatGPT 대화에 계속
full of
온갖
context of like every inspection report or like
점검 보고서 같은 컨텍스트를 채워 넣거나
wanting it to be like level the playing
정보 비대칭을
field between
저와
me and like the realtor to understand kind
부동산 중개인 사이에서 줄여서 대략
of all the dynamics and things that are
모든 역학관계와
going on.
진행 상황을 이해하려고 했습니다.
And it just feels like there should be
그러다 보니 이런 일을 해주는
an app for that.
앱이 있어야 한다고 느낍니다.
But simultaneously, I'm sure you took the PDFs
하지만 동시에, 아마 PDF들을
and just like dropped them into Gemini and
그냥 Gemini에 넣고
said
이렇게 말했겠지요,
like, well, summarize and tell me what's important
"요약해 주고 무엇이 중요한지
for me.
알려 달라"고요.
I guess I worry about, I worried about,
저는 좀 걱정이 됩니다. 예전에도 그랬고,
I still don't trust the models enough to
지금도 모델을 충분히 신뢰하지 못해서
be
프롬프팅을 많이 하지 않으면 정확하지 않을까 싶습니다. 게다가 이건
accurate without lots of prompting. And it's a
고가의 거래입니다. 그래서
high value transaction. So you don't want to
그냥
like
잘못된 데이터를 얻고 싶지 않습니다. 그래서 저는
get incorrect data out of it. So I
여전히 직접
still feel like you need to put in
노력을 들여야 한다고 느끼고, 그러면서도
the work and it feels like
모든 일을 대신해 주는 앱이
there should still be apps that just do
여전히 있어야 한다고
all the work for you.
생각합니다.
Did you see Karpathy release like sort of
Karpathy가 일종의
a LLM arena of a sort, which I
LLM 아레나 같은 것을 공개한 것 보셨습니까? 저는
mean, I do by like hand
말하자면 그걸 손으로
right now using tabs. It's like you have
지금 탭으로 하고 있습니다. 예를 들면
Claude open, you have Gemini open, you have
Claude를 열어두고, Gemini를 열어두고,
ChatGPT open,
ChatGPT도 열어두고,
and you give it the same task. And
똑같은 과제를 줍니다. 그리고
then you take the output from each. And
각각의 결과를 가져오고,
then I usually go to Claude
그다음에는 보통 Claude로
at that point. And I'm like, all right,
가서 이렇게 말합니다. "좋습니다,
Claude, this is what the other one said.
Claude, 다른 모델은 이렇게 말했습니다."
What do you think?
"어떻게 생각하십니까?"
And check each other's work. I actually think
이렇게 서로의 작업을 대조합니다. 저는 사실
that that particular behavior at the consumer,
소비자 측에서 이런 행동이
that level that we're doing, startups are doing
우리가 하는 이 수준으로 스타트업들도
as well. They are actually arbitraging
똑같이 하고 있다고 봅니다. 실제로 그들은
a lot of the models. I had some
여러 모델을 적극적으로 조합해 이득을 보고 있습니다. 저는
conversations with a number of founders where before
여러 창업자들과 대화를 했는데, 예전에는
they
그들이 예를 들어 OpenAI
might've been loyalists to, let's say, open AI
모델이나 Anthropic에 충성적이었을 수도 있습니다. 그런데 저는
models or Anthropic. And I just had some
최근에도 그들과 대화를 했습니다. 이들은
conversations recently with them. And these are founders
더 큰 회사를 운영하는 창업자들이고,
that are running larger companies like
시리즈 B 수준의 회사들입니다. AI에서는
series B level type of companies. With AI,
그들이 실제로 그런 것들을 전부 추상화해 버리고
they're actually abstracting all that away
오케스트레이션 레이어를 구축해서, 아마도
and building this orchestration layer where perhaps as
새 모델이 출시될 때마다
each new model release comes out,
그것들을 갈아 끼웠다 뺐다 할 수 있고, 또는
they can swap them in and out, or
특정 작업에 더 뛰어난 특정 모델을
they can use specific models that are better
필요한 곳에
at certain things
바로 그 용도로 쓰기도 합니다. 예를 들어
for just that. For example, I heard from
어떤 스타트업에서 들었는데요,
the startup, they use Gemini 3 to do
Gemini 3로
the context
컨텍스트
engineering, which they actually then fed into OpenAI
엔지니어링을 하고, 그 결과를 실제로 OpenAI에 넣어
to execute it. And they keep swapping it
실행한다고 합니다. 그리고 그들은 계속
as
새
new models come up and the winner for
모델이 나올 때마다 바꾸며, 각
each category or type of agent work is
카테고리나 에이전트 작업 유형마다
different.
승자가 달라진다는 것입니다.
And ultimately they can do this because it
그리고 궁극적으로 이것이 가능한 이유는
is all grounded based on the evals. And
모든 것이 평가(evals)에 기반해 정착되어 있기 때문입니다. 또
the evals are all
그 평가들은 전부
proprietary to them because they're a vertical AI
그들만의 독점 자산인데, 그들은 버티컬 AI
agent and they just work in a very
에이전트이고, 매우
regulated industry
규제가 강한 산업에서만
and they have this data set that just
일하면서, 자신들에게 가장
works the best for them. I think this
잘 맞는 데이터셋을 갖고 있기 때문입니다. 저는 이것이
is the new normal right
바로 지금의 새로운
now where people are expecting, yeah, that it's
표준이 되었다고 생각합니다. 사람들은 이제, 네,
cool that the model companies, they're spending all
모델 회사들이
this
막대한 돈을
money and making intelligence faster and better and
쏟아부어 지능을 더 빠르고 더 좋게 만드는 것이 멋지고, 또
we can all benefit. Let's just do the
우리 모두가 그 혜택을 볼 수 있으니, 그냥
best.
최선을 다하자는 것입니다.
It's almost like the era of Intel and
마치 Intel과
AMD with new architecture would come up. People
AMD가 새 아키텍처를 내놓던 시기와 비슷합니다. 사람들은
could just swap
그냥
them, right? Yeah, if it was at the
갈아 끼울 수 있었지요, 맞습니까? 네, 최상위 수준에서는
highest level, that angst around where's the value
가치가 어디에
going to accrue?
쌓일지에 대한 불안이
Is it going to go to the model
모델
companies or like the application layer, i.e.
회사로 갈지, 아니면 애플리케이션 레이어, 즉
the startups, feels like
스타트업으로 갈지 같은 문제는
that ebbs and flows in either direction a
한 해 동안 양쪽으로
little bit throughout the year to me. Like
조금씩 오르내리는 것처럼 느껴집니다. 예를 들어
I feel there are moments
어떤 순간에는
where Claude Code, amazing launch and it was
Claude Code가 정말 멋지게 출시되면서
like, oh, okay, like the model companies are
아, 그렇구나, 모델 회사들이
actually
실제로
going to play out the application layer. But
애플리케이션 레이어까지 가져가려는 것처럼 보이기도 합니다. 하지만
then to me at least it's all vibes
적어도 제게는 결국 다 분위기(vibes)로
based. Like the
결정되는 것 같습니다. 예를 들어
Gemini surge, especially over the last few months,
특히 지난 몇 달간의 Gemini 급상승은
just feels like it returns us to a
우리를 다시
world of where
그런 세계로
exactly that. Like the models are all essentially
되돌려 놓는 느낌입니다. 모델들은 본질적으로 모두
commoditizing each other and it's just like the
서로를 상품화(커모디티화)하고 있고, 결국
application layer and the startups are going to
애플리케이션 레이어와 스타트업들이
set up to have another fantastic year if
또 한 번 훌륭한 한 해를 보낼 준비가 되는 것처럼
that continues.
그런 흐름이 계속된다면 말입니다.
I'm curious what you think, Jared, with some,
Jared, 어떻게 생각하십니까? 특히
a lot of perhaps the negative comments on
부정적인 댓글들이 꽤 많은데,
Twitter
트위터에서요.
around, is this a bit of a bubble,
이게 약간의 거품인지에 대한 이야기와 관련해
an AI bubble? Yeah. When I talk to
AI 거품인지요? 네. 제가
undergrads, this is like a
학부생들과 이야기하면, 이건
common question that I get is like, oh,
제가 자주 받는 질문입니다. 예를 들면, 아,
like I heard it's a big AI bubble
AI가 큰 거품이라고 들었는데
because like there's all
왜냐하면
this like crazy round tripping going between NVIDIA
NVIDIA와
and OpenAI and like, is it all fake?
OpenAI 사이에서 미친 듯한 라운드트립이 일어나고, 이게 다 가짜 아닙니까?
Yeah.
네.
No, this is fantastic, right? Like people look
아니요, 이건 훌륭한 일입니다. 사람들이
at the telecom bubble and it's like there's
통신 버블을 보면
just,
그때는
you know, billions of dollars, like tens of
수십억 달러, 수백억 달러,
billions, hundreds of billions, just like
심지어 수천억 달러가
sort of sitting in a bunch of telecom
통신 인프라에
back in like the, you know, 90s. Actually,
90년대에 그냥 쌓여 있었습니다. 사실
that's why YouTube was
그게 YouTube가
able to exist, right? Like if you just
존재할 수 있었던 이유입니다, 맞습니까? 만약
have a whole bunch of extra bandwidth that
사용되지 않는 여분의 대역폭이 잔뜩 있고
isn't being used and
그리고
is relatively cheap, the cost is low enough
그게 비교적 싸다면, 비용이 충분히 낮아져서
for like something like YouTube to exist. Like
YouTube 같은 서비스가 존재할 수 있습니다. 즉
if there
만약
wasn't a glut of telecom, then like maybe
통신이 과잉 공급되지 않았다면, 아마
YouTube would have happened and just would have
유튜브는 결국 생겼겠지만 그저
happened
더 늦게
later. And then that, isn't that like sort
일어났을 뿐입니다. 그리고 그게, 여기서 우리가 말하는 게
of what we're talking about here? Like how
바로 그런 것 아닙니까? 그러니까
do we,
어떻게
we have to accelerate, right? We have the
더 빠르게 가속해야 합니다, 맞습니까? 우리는
age of intelligence, the rocks can talk, they
지능의 시대에 살고 있고, 바위도 말하며,
can think,
생각할 수 있고,
and they can do work and you just
일도 할 수 있는데, 여러분은 그냥
have to zap them more and you get
더 많은 전력을 공급하면 되고, 그러면
like smarter and smarter stuff at
점점 더 똑똑한 것들이
this point. I think the argument to college
이 시점에서는 그렇습니다. 저는 대학생들에게 하는 주장이
students is actually like, because there will be
사실 이런 것입니다. 앞으로 과잉 공급이 생길 것이기 때문에
a glut,
과잉 공급 말입니다,
there is an opportunity for you. And if
여러분에게 기회가 생긴다는 것입니다. 그리고 만약
there was not a glut, then there wouldn't
과잉 공급이 없다면, 그러면
be as much
그만큼
competition. The prices would be higher. The margins
경쟁이 많지 않을 것입니다. 가격은 더 높아지고, 마진은
lower in the stack would be higher, right?
스택 하단에서 더 높아질 것입니다, 맞습니까?
And then, you know, what's one of the
그리고, 아시다시피, 올해의 큰 이야기 중 하나가 무엇입니까?
big stories this year? Like Nvidia suddenly is
엔비디아가 갑자기 밀려나고 있다는 것입니다. 그러니까
on the outs. Like
입지가 흔들리고 있는 것입니다. 그러니까
I think their stock is today is like
오늘 주가가
around 170s or something. You know, I think
170달러대쯤인 것 같습니다. 아시다시피, 저는
I'm still a long-term
솔직히 여전히 장기적으로는
buy and hold, honestly. But for the moment,
매수 후 보유라고 생각합니다. 하지만 당장은,
people are like, oh, well, Gemini is so
사람들이 말하기를, 아, 제미니가 너무
good.
좋다고 합니다.
And all the, you know, nobody seems to
그리고, 아시다시피, 이제는 아무도
be Nvidia only now and everyone's buying AMD
엔비디아만 고집하지 않는 것 같고 모두가 AMD를
and everyone's,
사고 있고, 모두가,
you know, and TPUs are working. So, you
아시다시피, TPU도 잘 돌아갑니다. 그래서,
know, at the moment it looks like there's,
아시다시피, 지금은 마치
you know,
그러니까,
what does that mean? Like there's competition and
그게 무슨 뜻입니까? 경쟁이 있다는 뜻이고
it means that there will be more compute,
연산 자원이 더 많아진다는 뜻입니다,
not less. And then that means that probably
줄어드는 것이 아니라요. 그리고 그러면 아마
a little bit better things for all of
모든
the big LLM
대형 LLM
companies like sort of the, you know, the
기업들, 그러니까, 아시다시피,
AI labs, they get a little bit of
AI 랩들이 조금
power, but,
힘을 얻게 되겠지만,
you know, they too are in competition with
아시다시피, 그들 또한 서로 경쟁하고 있습니다.
one another. So then what does that mean?
그렇다면 그게 무슨 뜻입니까?
Well,
그러면,
then it's, you know, go up another level
그러면, 아시다시피, 한 단계 위로 올라가야 합니다
in this stack, right? Like as long as
이 스택에서요, 맞습니까? 즉,
there are a great many
아주 많은
AI labs that are in a deep competition
AI 랩들이 치열하게 경쟁
with one another, then that's even better for
하고 있다면, 그러면 그것은 오히려 더 좋습니다,
that college
그 대학
student who's about to start a company at
학생에게요. 즉, 애플리케이션 레이어에서 회사를 시작하려는
the application level. Yeah, I think that's exactly
학생에게요. 네, 저는 그게 정확히
right.
맞다고 생각합니다.
It's like people are asking this question, like,
사람들이 이런 질문을 합니다. 즉,
is it a bubble? That's maybe a question
"거품입니까?"라는 질문은 어쩌면
that's
정말
really relevant. If you're like the equivalent of
적절한 질문입니다. 예컨대
like Comcast, like if you're Nvidia, that's a
Comcast 같은 존재이거나 엔비디아라면, 그건
very
매우
relevant question. Like, oh, are people overbuilding GPU
중요한 질문입니다. 예를 들어 사람들이 GPU 용량을 과잉 구축하고 있습니까?
capacity, but like the college students, they're
하지만 대학생들은
not Comcast. They're actually like YouTube. If you're
Comcast가 아닙니다. 사실 유튜브에 가깝습니다. 만약
doing a startup in your dorm room, it's
기숙사 방에서 스타트업을 한다면, 그것은
like
마치
the AI equivalent of like YouTube and like
AI에서 유튜브 같은 것에 해당하는 것이 있다고 하더라도
kind of doesn't really matter that much. Maybe
사실 그리 중요하지 않습니다. 어쩌면
Nvidia's
엔비디아의
talk will go down next year. I don't
주가가 내년에 내려갈 것이라는 얘기가 나올 수도 있습니다. 저는
know. But like, even if it does, that
잘 모르겠습니다. 하지만 설령 그렇더라도 그것이
doesn't actually mean
곧바로
that it's like a bad time to be
AI 스타트업을
working on an AI startup. Yeah, it's what
하는 데 나쁜 시기라는 뜻은 아닙니다. 네, 이는
Zuck said in a
저커버그가
podcast early this year, I think, right? It's
올해 초 팟캐스트에서 말한 내용과 비슷합니다, 맞지요? 요지는
like Meta may end up over investing like
메타가 결국
a significant
상당한
amount in like the capex and infrastructure, but
규모로 CAPEX와 인프라에 과잉 투자하게 될 수도 있지만,
like they essentially have to, the big companies
본질적으로는 그럴 수밖에 있고, 대기업들은
have to do it because they can't just
그렇게 해야 합니다. 그냥
like sit on the sidelines. And in the
옆에서 지켜보고만 있을 수는 없습니다. 그리고 만약
case, like demand falls
수요가
off a cliff for some reason, it's their
어떤 이유로든 급락한다면, 그것은 그들의
capex, not the startup's capex. And there's still
CAPEX이지 스타트업의 CAPEX가 아닙니다. 그리고 여전히
going to be
앞으로도
tons of infrastructure and ideas to still continue
계속 만들어 갈 인프라와 아이디어가 아주 많이
building. There was this book written by this
남아 있을 것입니다. 카를로타 페레즈라는
economist called Carlota Perez, who studied a lot
경제학자가 쓴 책이 있는데, 그분은 많은
of tech trends, and it studies a lot
기술 트렌드를 연구했고, 또 많은
of
기술
technology revolutions. And it summarizes that there's really
혁명도 연구했습니다. 그리고 실제로는 두 단계가 있다고
two phases. There's the phase of
요약합니다. 첫 번째는
installation, which is where a lot of the
설치 단계인데, 여기서 많은
very heavy capex investment come in. And then
막대한 CAPEX 투자가 들어옵니다. 그리고 다음은
there's the
바로
deployment phase where really ripples, where it rips,
전개 단계인데, 실제로 파급이 일어나고 본격적으로 확산되며,
and then everything explodes in terms of abundance.
풍요로움의 측면에서 모든 것이 폭발합니다.
And during the initial phase of installation is
그리고 설치 단계의 초기에는
where it feels like a bubble. There's a
거품처럼 느껴집니다. 약간의
bit of a
광풍이
frenzy because it starts first with a, there's
있는데, 처음에는 이런 식으로 시작합니다. 즉,
this new technology that's amazing, which happened
정말 놀라운 새로운 기술이 등장하고, 이것이
with the ChatGPT moment in 2023. Everyone got
2023년의 ChatGPT 순간에서 일어났습니다. 모두가
super excited about the tech, and then everyone's
그 기술에 매우 흥분했고, 그러고 나서 모두가
got
더
super hyped and got into investing into a
더욱 고무되어
lot of the infrastructure with buying a lot
인프라에 많이 투자하기 시작했고, 많은
of GPUs and
GPU를
all the giant gigawatt data center build out.
사들이며 거대한 기가와트급 데이터센터를 구축했습니다.
And then people say, but what is the
그러고 나서 사람들은 묻습니다. 그러면 도대체
demand? What are
수요는 무엇입니까? 어떤
going to be all the applications to be
애플리케이션들이
built out? I think right now we're in
만들어질 것입니까? 저는 지금 우리가
that transition,
그 전환기에 있다고
which is actually really good news for startup
생각합니다. 그리고 이것은 사실 스타트업
founders because they are not involved into the
창업자들에게 매우 좋은 소식인데, 그들은
building the data centers, but they're going to
데이터센터를 짓는 일에는 관여하지 않고,
build the next generation of applications in the
대신 다음 세대 애플리케이션을
deployment phase when it really proliferates. And what
정말로 확산되는 전개 단계에서 만들 것이기 때문입니다. 그리고
happened, just going back to the analogy with
인터넷 시대에 대한 비유로 돌아가 보면,
with the era of the internet, before the
인터넷 시대를 보자면, 2000년 이전에는
2000, there was a lot of heavy capex
막대한 CAPEX
investment into
투자가
the telcos, right? Those were giant projects that
통신사들에 들어갔습니다. 그런 것들은
college students wouldn't be involved,
대학생들이 관여할 만한
but they were very heavily invested. And in
프로젝트가 아니었지만, 매우 크게 투자되었습니다. 그리고
some cases were over invested. I mean,
어떤 경우에는 과잉투자이기도 했습니다. 예를 들면,
there's a whole thing with dark fiber and
다크 파이버 같은 것과
some pipes that are not used and that's
사용되지 않는 일부 회선들이 있었는데, 그것은
fine.
괜찮습니다.
The internet ended up being still a giant
인터넷은 결국 여전히 거대한
economic driver. And what that means is startups
경제적 동력이 되었습니다. 그리고 그것이 의미하는 바는
like the
바로
future Facebook or the future Google are yet
미래의 페이스북이나 미래의 구글 같은
to be started because those come in in
스타트업들이 아직 시작되지 않았다는 것이며, 그런 것들은
the deployment
전개
phase. Because right now I think things are
단계에서 등장하기 때문입니다. 왜냐하면 지금은 저는
still getting built up. I do think the
여전히 여러 것들이 구축되고 있다고 생각합니다. 그리고
foundation lab
파운데이션 모델
companies and GPUs very much are falling into
기업들과 GPU는 분명히
the bucket of infrastructure.
인프라 범주에 들어간다고 생각합니다.
Yeah. I mean, it's interesting to watch how
네. 그러니까, 이런 것들이 어떻게
this stuff is evolving a little bit. So
조금씩 진화하는지 지켜보는 것이 흥미롭습니다. 그래서
do you remember
기억하십니까,
summer 24, there was a company called StarCloud
24년 여름에 스타클라우드라는 회사가
that came out and was one of the
등장했고, 그중에서도
first to come out and
가장 먼저
say, we're going to make data centers in
우리는 우주에 데이터센터를 만들겠다고
space. And what was the reaction when, you
말했습니다. 그리고 그때 반응이 어땠습니까, 그러니까
know,
아시다시피,
people laugh at them on the internet. Yeah.
사람들이 인터넷에서 그들을 비웃었죠. 네.
They said, that's the stupidest idea ever.
그들은 "역대 가장 멍청한 아이디어"라고 말했습니다.
You know, I guess 18 months later, suddenly
그런데 18개월 뒤인 지금은 갑자기
Google's doing it. Elon's doing it.
구글도 하고 있고, 일론도 하고 있습니다.
So now it mentions it in every interview
그래서 이제는 모든 인터뷰에서 그것을 언급한다고
now, apparently.
합니다, 지금은.
Is that right?
정말 그런가요?
It seems to be like his top talking
그분의 가장 중요한
point.
이야깃거리인 것 같습니다.
Yeah. And so, I mean, why is that?
네. 그런데, 그러면 왜 그런 것입니까?
Like, I feel like one of the aspects
제 생각에 그 이유 중 하나는
is that like,
그러니까,
part of the infrastructure build out right now
지금 진행되는 인프라 확장의 한 부분이
that's so intense is like, we literally don't
너무 격렬한 이유가, 저희가 말 그대로
have
전혀
power generation. Boom Supersonic, instead of making supersonic
전력 생산 능력이 없기 때문입니다. Boom Supersonic은 지금 초음속
jets right now,
제트기를 만드는 대신,
is on this good quest to create enough
이 많은 AI 데이터
power for a bunch of these AI data
센터들에 필요한 충분한
centers that are being
전력을 만들기 위한
built right now. They use jet engines. And
프로젝트를 진행하고 있습니다. 그들은 제트 엔진을 씁니다. 그리고
even those like are so bad, you know,
그마저도 상황이 매우 좋지 않은데,
the supply chain
공급망이
for jet engines to generate power for data
데이터센터 전력 생산용 제트 엔진에 대한
centers is so backed up that, you know,
수요로 너무 밀려 있어서,
you would have had
이것들을 확보하려면
to have ordered these things, you know, two
사실 2년
or three years ago just to even have
또는 3년 전에 주문했어야 하고,
it in two or three
그래야 2년이나 3년
years from now. You know, these constraints, uh,
뒤에나 받을 수 있습니다. 이런 제약들이
end up like influencing like fairly directly
결국 꽤 직접적으로 영향을 미쳐서
what the giant tech companies need to do
거대 기술 기업들이 무엇을 해야 하는지,
to win the game three or five years
3년이나 5년
out.
뒤에 게임에서 이기기 위해서입니다.
Like suddenly there's not enough land, you know,
갑자기 땅이 충분하지 않게 됩니다, 아시겠지만,
in America, we can't build. The regulations are
미국에서는 짓지를 못합니다. 규제가
too
너무
high. In California, we have CEQA, which is
강합니다. 캘리포니아에는 CEQA가 있는데, 그건
totally abused by the environmental lobby to stop
환경 로비가 완전히 악용해서
all
모든
innovation and building housing. By the way, we
혁신과 주택 건설을 막는 데 씁니다. 그리고 저희는
just don't have enough terrestrially like to just
지상에서 그냥
do the things that society sort of needs
사회가 필요로 하는 일들을
right now. So, you know, the escape valve
지금 당장 할 만큼의 여력이 없습니다. 그래서, 탈출구는
is like,
그러니까,
actually, let's just do it in space. Yeah.
사실 우주에서 그냥 해버리자는 겁니다. 네.
Come to think about, we, we kind of
생각해보니, 저희가
have
거의
the trifecta of YC companies that are solving
데이터 센터 확장 문제를 해결하는 YC 회사 삼총사를
the data center buildup problem. Well, you need
갖고 있는 셈이네요. 음, 필요한 건
fusion
핵융합
energy. Yeah. Yeah. Well, we have the company
에너지죠. 네, 네. 그리고 저희에겐 그 회사가 있습니다,
that's solving the no land problem by building
땅이 없는 문제를 해결하려고
the data centers in space. We have boom
데이터 센터를 우주에 짓는 회사요. 또 Boom
and helium, which are solving that we don't
과 Helium이 있는데, 저희가
have an energy
에너지
problem. I just found today, uh, a space
문제가 없도록 해결하고 있죠. 오늘은, 음, 우주
fusion company that just graduated called Zephyr fusion.
핵융합 회사 하나를 찾았는데, 막 졸업한 Zephyr Fusion입니다.
That's a cool one. And they actually had
멋진 회사죠. 그리고 그들은 실제로
a great seed round out of demo day.
데모데이 이후에 훌륭한 시드 라운드를 했습니다.
They're in their forties,
그분들은 40대이고,
they're national lab engineers who their entire careers,
국립 연구소 엔지니어들로서 커리어 내내
they were building, you know, tokamaks and
아시겠지만 토카막 같은 것과
fusion energy. And they came into the lab
핵융합 에너지를 만들던 분들입니다. 어느 날 연구소에 들어와서
one day, they looked at the physics, they,
그들이 물리를 보고,
you know, looked at the
그러니까,
math and the models and they said, you
수학과 모델을 들여다보고는, 이렇게 말했죠,
know what, if we did this in space,
있잖아요, 이걸 우주에서 하면
it would actually pencil.
실제로 타산이 맞을 겁니다.
And so that's, they're on like this sort
그래서 그들은 일종의
of grand next five, 10 year quest to
앞으로 5년, 10년짜리 거대한 퀘스트를 하고 있는데,
actually manifest it,
그걸 실제로 구현해서,
to actually create it in space, uh, because
우주에서 진짜로 만들어내려는 겁니다, 음, 왜냐하면
the equations say that it is possible. And,
방정식이 가능하다고 말하거든요. 그리고,
uh,
음,
if they do it, it's actually the only
그걸 해낸다면, 그게 사실상 유일한
path to gigawatts of energy, uh, up there
기가와트급 에너지를 얻는 경로가 됩니다, 음, 저 위
in space. So,
우주에서요. 그래서,
you know, it might be, you know, an
아시겠지만, 그게 어쩌면
even more perfect trifecta, uh, shortly.
곧 더 완벽한 삼총사가 될 수도 있겠네요, 음.
Yeah. Something else I feel like happened over
네. 제가 보기엔 올해 동안 또 하나 일어난 일이 있었습니다.
the course of this year is the, um,
올해 한 해 동안의 흐름 중 하나가, 음,
interest in starting model companies. Like, I guess
모델 회사를 시작하려는 관심이 커진 것 같습니다. 그러니까, 제 생각에는
that maybe at both ends, there's like
어쩌면 양쪽 끝 모두에 그런 흐름이 있는 것 같습니다만,
the people who can raise the capital to
자본을 조달할 수 있는 사람들은
go and actually try and build a head
나가서 실제로 정면 경쟁자를
on competitor to
만들어 보려고 시도해서
open AI, which there are very, very few,
OpenAI와 겨루려 하지만, 그런 사례는 정말, 정말 드뭅니다.
like maybe have ILIO with SSI, but then
예를 들면 SSI의 ILIO 같은 경우가 있을지 모르지만, 그보다는
more so within YC,
YC 내부에서는 오히려
people trying to build like smaller models. Um,
더 작은 모델을 만들려는 사람들이 더 많습니다. 음,
I've certainly had more of those in the
저도 확실히 그런 팀을
last few
최근 몇
batches than before, like whether it's sort of
배치에서 예전보다 더 많이 봤습니다. 예를 들면
like a models run on edge devices or
엣지 디바이스에서 구동되는 모델이거나
maybe like a voice
아니면 음성
model specific to a particular language. And I'm
특정 언어에 특화된 모델 같은 것들입니다. 그리고 저는
curious to see if that trend continues going
그런 추세가 계속될지 궁금합니다, 다시
back
되돌아가
to this early era of YC. Actually, we
YC의 초기 시대로 보면, 사실 우리는
sort of saw the explosion of just startups
스타트업이 만들어지는 폭발을
being created
어느 정도 목격했습니다.
and maybe especially SaaS startups. Partly what, what,
그리고 아마 특히 SaaS 스타트업이 그랬습니다. 부분적으로는, 뭐,
um, fed that was just knowledge about startups
음, 그걸 뒷받침한 것은 스타트업에 대한 지식이
became more dispersed. There wasn't like a canon
더 널리 퍼졌기 때문입니다. 인터넷에는 정전 같은
of library information on the internet about like
자료가 거의 없었습니다. 예를 들면
how to start a startup, how to build
어떻게 스타트업을 시작하는지, 어떻게
software. And then over like a decade that
소프트웨어를 만드는지요. 그리고 약 10년에 걸쳐 그것이
just became more
점점 더
commonplace and that just exploded like society's knowledge
보편화되면서, 사회의 지식이 폭발적으로 늘었습니다.
of startups and how to build things.
스타트업과 무언가를 만드는 방법에 대해서요.
And it's maybe feels like maybe we're going
그리고 어쩌면 지금은 우리가
through that moment in sort of the AI
AI 분야에서 그런 순간을
research
연구가
meets like actually building things with, with training
모델을 학습시키며 실제로 무언가를 만드는 일과, 그 지점에서
models. I think we are absolutely going
만나는 과정을 확실히
through that right now. Yes. Like where it's
지금 겪고 있다고 생각합니다. 네. 그러니까 그게
going from being a very rare skill set
아주 희귀한 기술 조합에서
to a more common
더 흔한 기술 조합으로
one. Cause like open AI a decade ago,
바뀌고 있기 때문입니다. 예를 들어 10년 전의 OpenAI는,
it was like a rare, like you needed,
정말 드문 경우였고, 그러니까 필요했던 것이,
you need like a,
그러니까 그런,
a unique combination of skills, right? You need
독특한 기술 조합이 필요했지요. 연구자적 사고도 필요하고
like your researcher brain,
연구자적 머리도 필요하고,
your sort of like engineering brain, maybe like
일종의 엔지니어링 감각도 필요하고, 어쩌면
your sort of finance business brain.
재무나 비즈니스 감각도 필요했습니다.
Wait, wait, wait. So did you just describe
잠깐, 잠깐, 잠깐요. 그러면 방금
Ilya, Greg, and Sam?
일리야, 그렉, 그리고 샘을 묘사하신 건가요?
You got it.
맞습니다.
That was like a rare team, right? There
그런 팀은 정말 희귀했지요. 그때는
was, wasn't that configuration of team around very
그런 팀 구성이 주변에 그리
much. And now
많지 않았습니다. 그런데 이제
a decade later, there's like a plethora of
10년이 지난 지금은, 그런 배경을 가진 사람들이 아주 많습니다.
people who have like the research background,
연구 배경을 가진 사람들도 많고,
the engineering background, um, the startup capital raising,
엔지니어링 배경도 있고, 음, 스타트업 자본 조달
um, background, or at least can be taught
음, 경험도 있거나, 적어도 그런 것들을
how to do all of that kind of
하는 법을 배울 수 있습니다. 그리고 저는 그게 그냥
stuff. And I'm curious if that would just
그런 것들 전부를 하려면 필요한데, 그리고 저는 그것이 단지
mean we'll just see more
더 많이 보게 된다는 뜻인지 궁금합니다.
applied AI company starting, and maybe there'll be
적용형 AI 회사를 더 많이 시작하게 되는 것인지, 그리고 어쩌면
like even more models to choose from for
다양한 특정 과업을 위해 선택할 수 있는 모델도 더 많아질지요.
all
모든
the various specific tasks. I think so. I
여러 특정 과업에서요. 저도 그렇게 생각합니다. 또
think the other thing that's even contributing and
하나 더 기여하면서 이것을 더
making
큰 눈덩이로
this an even bigger snowball is because of
만드는 이유는 바로
RL. I think there's all these new open
RL 때문입니다. 새로운 오픈
source models that
소스 모델들이 있고,
people are doing the fine tune on top
사람들이 그 위에 파인튜닝을
of it with a particular RL environment and
특정 RL 환경과
task. So it is very
과업에 맞춰서 하고 있으니, 그러므로 충분히
possible that you can create the best domain
가능합니다, 최고의 도메인
specific, let's say, healthcare model trained on a
특화, 이를테면 헬스케어 모델을, 어떤
generic open source model by just doing fine
그냥 무난하게만 해도 범용 오픈소스 모델은
tuning on it and doing RL. It beats
거기에 파인튜닝과 RL을 하면, 그것이
the regular big model.
일반적인 대형 모델을 이깁니다.
Actually, I've heard and seen a number of
사실 저는 여러 사례를 듣고 직접 본 적도 있는데,
startups where their domain specific model beats, uh,
도메인 특화 모델이, 어, 이기는 스타트업들이
open
오픈
AI, let's say on healthcare. There's this particular
AI를 예컨대 헬스케어 분야에서 이깁니다. 특히 어떤
YC startup that told me that they collected
YC 스타트업이 저에게, 그들이 모은 것이
the best
최고의
data set for, for healthcare and they ended
헬스케어용 데이터셋이었고, 결국
up performing better than open AI and a
OpenAI보다 더 나은 성능을 보였으며
lot of the
여러
benchmarks for, for healthcare with only 8 billion
헬스케어 벤치마크에서도 파라미터가 80억 개뿐인데도
parameters. I guess what's funny is, uh, you
그랬다고 했습니다. 재미있는 점은, 어, 결국
do need
필요한 것이
to have a post-training infrastructure. You know,
사후 학습 인프라라는 점입니다. 아시다시피,
we've also had YC companies where, uh, they
저희도 YC 회사들 중에, 어, 그들이
had something that
어떤 것으로
beat open AI, uh, you know, GPT 3
OpenAI, 그러니까 GPT-3
.5 and they were doing fine tuning with
.5를 이겼고 RL로 파인튜닝을 하고 있었던
RL, but then, uh, yeah, GPT 4.5
경우가 있었습니다. 그런데, 어, 네, GPT-4.5가
and
그리고
then 5.1 came out and, uh, you
그다음 5.1이 나오면서, 어, 그들의
know, basically blew their fine tuning out of
파인튜닝이 사실상 완전히
the water. You have to keep
무력화되었습니다. 계속
going. Yeah. Yeah. You gotta keep going. Yeah.
해 나가야 합니다. 네. 네. 계속해야 합니다. 네.
I mean, you actually have to continue to,
그러니까 실제로는 계속해서
uh, get to the
어, 최전선까지
edge. Anything else, uh, that really sort of
도달해야 합니다. 또 다른 것으로, 어, 지난 1년 동안
stood out from this past year that jumps
정말 두드러졌던 것이
out to you?
떠오르시나요?
Uh, it's funny. We started the year with
어, 재미있습니다. 저희는 한 해를
one of our episodes that got a lot
조회수가 많이 나온 에피소드 중 하나로
of views around
바로
vibe coding. I think we were talking about
바이브 코딩을 다뤘습니다. 당시에는
it more as observing a behavior that was
발생하던 행동을 관찰하는 정도로
happening
이야기하고
from our founders. And I was surprised to
있었습니다. 그런데 저는
see that this became like a giant category.
이것이 거대한 카테고리가 된 것을 보고 놀랐습니다.
There's
그리고
lots of companies that are winning. I mean,
이기고 있는 회사가 정말 많습니다. 예를 들어,
we have Replit, there's Emergence, there's a bunch
Replit도 있고 Emergence도 있고, 그 외에도
of them.
여러 곳이 있습니다.
Varun Mohan had gone over to Google. He
Varun Mohan은 Google로 갔고,
released anti-gravity. And, uh, did you guys
anti-gravity를 공개했습니다. 그리고, 어, 여러분은
see the video?
그 영상을 보셨나요?
I actually, I'm sort of curious whether they
저는 사실 그들이
actually used nano banana or any of these
nano banana나 이런
video
영상
gen things. Cause it's like a little too
생성 도구를 실제로 썼는지 궁금합니다. 약간 너무
perfect, but Google has the budget to do
완벽해 보이는데, Google은
the high
높은 수준의
production value video, but it's, you know, Varun
제작비 영상을 만들 예산이 있습니다. 그런데 영상에는 Varun이
at the keyboard and then, you know,
키보드 앞에 있고, 또
Sergey is like right behind him. So I
Sergey가 바로 뒤에 서 있는 듯합니다. 그래서
was like, it was very cinematic. Anyway, I
매우 시네마틱하다고 느꼈습니다. 어쨌든 저는
think Sundar was, uh,
Sundar도, 어,
you know, also not only talking about, um,
아시다시피, 음, 우주 데이터 센터뿐 아니라
space data centers, uh, he was also talking
그것에 대해서 이야기했을 뿐만 아니라, 또한
about vibe
바이브
coding and I knew that I was a
코딩에 대해서도 말하고 있었다고 봅니다. 그리고 저는 제가
little bit trolling back, but knowing what we
약간 되받아치는 농담을 하고 있다는 것을 알지만, 우리가
know, I mean, yes, vibe
아는 바를 생각하면, 그러니까 네, 바이브
coding is not, you know, completely usable and
코딩은 완전히 사용할 수 있고
trustable for, uh, you know, a hundred percent
신뢰할 수 있는 것이, 어, 100%는 아닙니다.
of your
여러분의
coding period. Like this, you know, it is
코딩 기간 전체에 대해서 말입니다. 그러니까, 아시다시피,
not true that you can like ship a
바로 출시할 수 있다는 말이
hundred, a hundred percent
100%, 그러니까 100%로
solid production code today as of 2020 and
완전히 견고한 프로덕션 코드를 오늘 당장, 2020년 기준으로도
the end of 2025.
2025년 말 기준으로도 가능하다는 것은 사실이 아닙니다.
Yeah. I was thinking about things that surprised
네. 저는 2025년에 저를 놀라게 했던 것들을
me in 2025. And I think perhaps the
생각해 보고 있었습니다. 그리고 아마도
thing that most
가장
surprised me is the extent to which I
놀라웠던 것은 제가
feel like the AI economy stabilized. Like I
AI 경제가 안정화되었다고 느끼는 정도입니다. 그러니까
feel like when we did
저는 우리가
this episode at the end of 2024, it
2024년 말에 이 에피소드를 했을 때는
felt like we were still in the middle
여전히 한가운데에
of a period of incredibly
믿을 수 없을 만큼
rapid change where the ground was shifting under
급격한 변화의 시기였고, 발밑이
our feet and like nobody knew when the
흔들리는 듯했으며, 누구도
other shoe
다음 충격이
might drop and like what exactly was going
언제 올지, 그리고 정확히 무엇이
to happen with startups and AI and the
스타트업과 AI, 그리고
economy. Now I feel like
경제에 어떤 영향을 줄지 몰랐습니다. 지금은 저는
we've kind of settled into like a fairly
우리가 비교적
stable AI economy where we have like the
안정적인 AI 경제로 어느 정도 자리 잡았다고 느끼며,
model layer
모델 레이어
companies and the application layer companies and seem,
회사들과 애플리케이션 레이어 회사들이 있고,
and the infrastructure layer companies,
인프라스트럭처 레이어 회사들도 있으며,
it seems like everyone is going to make
모두가
a lot of money and there's kind of
많은 돈을 벌게 될 것 같고, 어느 정도
like a relative playbook
상대적으로 표준적인 플레이북이
for how to build an AI native company
AI 네이티브 회사를
on top of the models. I feel like
모델 위에서 어떻게 만들지에 대해 생긴 것 같습니다. 저는
things really kind of matured
여러 면에서 정말로 성숙해졌다고
in that way. Which feels it's all downstream
느낍니다. 이는 결국
of like the models themselves have incrementally
모델 자체가 올해 점진적으로
improved this year, but there haven't been like
개선되기는 했지만,
major steps forward that have shaken everything up,
모든 것을 뒤흔들 만한 큰 도약은 없었다는 점에서
which is, has a knock on effect. Many
비롯된 것 같습니다. 그 결과로, 몇
episodes ago, we talked about how it was
에피소드 전에는
felt easier than
그 어느 때보다도
ever to pivot and find a startup idea.
피벗하고 스타트업 아이디어를 찾기가 쉬웠다고 이야기했습니다.
Because if you could just survive, if you
왜냐하면 버티기만 하면,
just wait a few
몇
months, there was likely going to be some
달만 기다려도 아마도
like big announcement that would completely make a
완전히 새로운
new set
아이디어들의
of ideas possible and create more opportunities to
가능성을 열고 더 많은 기회를
build things. It certainly feels like that has
만들어 줄 큰 발표가 있었기 때문입니다. 확실히 그런 속도는
slowed down. And so like finding ideas is
느려진 듯합니다. 그래서 아이디어를 찾는 일이
sort of returning to sort of normal levels
어느 정도 정상적인 난이도 수준으로
of difficulty,
돌아가고 있는 것 같고,
in my experience, not for hours. I agree.
제 경험상 그렇습니다. 저도 동의합니다.
I'll tell you what's not a surprise. Do
놀랍지 않은 이야기도 말씀드리겠습니다. 혹시
you remember
기억하시나요,
that report, AI 2027, where it was just
AI 2027이라는 보고서가 있었는데, 그것은
sort of like this doomer piece that said
일종의 종말론적 글로서
like, oh, well,
그러니까, 음,
society is going to start falling apart in
사회가
2027. But, you know, at some point, they
2027년에 무너져 내리기 시작할 것이라고 했습니다. 그런데 어느 시점에
quietly revised it
조용히 내용을 수정해서
to say that it wasn't 2027, but they
2027년이 아니라고 했지만,
kept the title. Maybe it's not a surprise.
제목은 그대로 두었습니다. 어쩌면 이것도 놀랄 일은 아닙니다.
Like I was always a
저는 원래부터
little bit of a skeptic of like this
이런
fast takeoff argument, because even with the scaling
패스트 테이크오프 논증과 관련해, 스케일링
law, it is
법칙이 있더라도,
log linear. So it is slower, it requires
그 성장은 로그-선형입니다. 그래서 더 느리고,
like 10x more compute, and it's still sort
예를 들어 컴퓨팅이 10배 더 필요하며, 그래도
of, you know,
말하자면,
topping out, right. And that's one form of
한계에 다다르는 것입니다. 그리고 이것이 한 가지 형태의
good news. Another form of it's weird to
좋은 소식입니다. 또 다른 형태로는 이것을
call this good
좋은 소식이라고 부르기엔 이상하지만,
news, but human beings don't like change. In
소위 '좋은 소식'이 하나 더 있는데, 인간은 변화를 좋아하지 않습니다.
our previous episode, where we sort of blew
지난 에피소드에서 저희가
up that
그
MIT report that said that, you know, 98
MIT 보고서를 다뤘는데, 거기서는 98
% or 90% of enterprise AI projects
퍼센트 또는 90퍼센트의 기업 AI 프로젝트가
fail. Well, it turns out that
실패한다고 했습니다. 그런데 알고 보니
90% of enterprises don't know how to
기업의 90퍼센트는
do, you know, IT, let alone AI. It's
IT조차 제대로 못하며, AI는 더더욱 그렇습니다.
weird to say that
이게
that's a good thing. But in the context
좋은 일이라고 말하기는 이상하지만, 패스트 테이크오프 맥락에서는
of fast takeoff, like, that is a real
이것이 실제로
break on the ability
이 새롭고 믿기 어려울 정도로 강력한 기술이
of this new, really insane technology from actually
실제로 사회에 스며드는 것을
permeating society. I love to accelerate, but like,
가로막는 큰 제동이 됩니다. 저는 가속을 좋아하지만,
it's weird to say, like, oh, well, actually,
이 경우에는 '사실은'
in this case, maybe that's a good thing,
그게 좋은 일일지도 모른다고 말하는 것이
right? Like,
이상하기는 합니다.
it is a shockingly powerful technology. But, you
정말 놀라울 정도로 강력한 기술입니다. 하지만
know, between being log linear scaling,
아시다시피, 로그-선형 스케일링이라는 점과
and human beings really don't like change, like
인간은 변화를 정말 좋아하지 않으며,
organizationally speaking, society will absorb
조직적으로 말하면 사회가
this technology, everyone will have enough time to
이 기술을 흡수할 것이고, 모두가 충분한 시간을 갖고
sort of process it, like culture will catch
어느 정도 이를 소화할 시간이 생기고, 문화도 따라잡을
up,
것입니다.
governments will be able to respond to it,
정부도 이에 대응할 수 있을 것입니다.
not in like a frantic SB 1047 sort
허둥대는 SB 1047 같은
of like, you know,
그런 식이 아니라,
let's stop all the compute past 10 to
‘10의 26제곱을 넘는 컴퓨팅은 전부 멈추자’ 같은,
the 26, right? Like just these knee jerk
그렇지요? 이런 반사적인
responses
대응들
to technology. We're excited about the Arc AGI
기술에 대한 대응입니다. 저희는 Arc AGI
prize is, you know, going to come in
프라이즈가, 아시다시피, 들어와서
and do the
그
winter 26 batch as a nonprofit. The funny
Winter 26 배치를 비영리로 진행할 거라는 점이 기대됩니다. 재미있는
thing about that is like, yeah, maybe there's
점은, 네, 어쩌면 지금
a team right now that is climbing the
Arc AGI 리더보드를
leaderboard of Arc AGI, and they're going to
올라가고 있는 팀이 있고, 그들이
accelerate this
이걸
thing again.
또다시 가속화할지도 모른다는 것입니다.
Something that surprised me to relate to that
그와 관련해서 제게 놀라웠던 점은
with the startups is I remember around this
스타트업 쪽에서, 제가 이쯤
time last
작년
year, we were talking about how companies are
이 시기에, 회사들이 어떻게
getting to a million dollars ARR and raising
연간 반복 매출(ARR) 100만 달러에 도달하고
series
시리즈
A's without hiring, like some cases, not hiring
A를 채용 없이도 받는다는 얘기를 했다는 것입니다, 어떤 경우엔 채용을
anyone, just the founders, maybe hiring one person,
아무도 채용하지 않고 창업자들만 있거나, 한 명만 채용하기도 했습니다,
which just felt very unusual. I feel like
그게 정말 이례적으로 느껴졌습니다. 그런데
a year on, that hasn't translated into, okay,
1년이 지난 지금, 그게 ‘좋아, 그러면’으로 이어지지는 않았고,
and then they went and hit like 10
그 다음에
million ARR, or they scaled without adding any
ARR 1,000만 달러를 찍었거나, 사람을
more people to.
더 늘리지 않고도 스케일했다로 이어지지는 않았습니다.
No, they turned around and started hiring like
아니요, 그들은 돌아서서
actual teams.
실제 팀을 채용하기 시작했습니다.
Yeah. Like post series A, it actually largely
네. 시리즈 A 이후에는, 사실 대부분
feels like the playbook is the same and
플레이북은 같고
the companies
회사들은
might be smaller for the same amount of
같은
revenue, but it feels it's entirely because they
매출 규모 대비 더 작을 수 있지만, 그건 전적으로 그들이
hit the
매출을
revenue so fast and there's still just bottlenecked
너무 빨리 달성했고, 여전히 병목이
on how long it takes to hire people
사람을 채용하는 데 걸리는 시간에 있어서
versus they
있기 때문이지, 그들이
have demand for less people.
더 적은 인력을 필요로 해서가 아닙니다.
I still think there is like, you know,
저는 여전히,
some effect, but it is not like open
어떤 효과는 있다고 보지만, 완전히
and shut. It is not like you
명확한 건 아닙니다. 여러분이
don't have to hire executives anymore. I think
더 이상 임원을 채용하지 않아도 된다는 뜻은 아닙니다. 저는
they're like, there might be a case of
그런 경우가 있을 수도 있다고
two foie
푸아그라 스타트업 두
gras startups, like one being Harvey and the
곳이 있는데, 하나는 Harvey이고 다른 하나는
other one being open evidence, right? Harvey,
Open Evidence입니다. Harvey는,
the founders are incredible. They were very early.
창업자들이 대단합니다. 아주 일찍 시작했습니다.
And then there's this sort of idea of
그리고 또 이런 생각이 있습니다.
like,
그러니까,
for VCs, you could just go down Sand
VC 입장에서는 Sand
Hill Road and like the fixes in, like
Hill Road를 쭉 돌면서, 승부가 이미 정해져 있는 것처럼
you just sort of block out
그들을 전부
all of them. And then all the people,
그냥 차단해 버릴 수 있다는 것입니다. 그리고 그 사람들,
you know, maybe 30 people who could write
아마 30명 정도가
checks of like 10 to
1,000만 달러에서
a hundred million dollars. And if you just
1억 달러 규모의 수표를 쓸 수 있습니다. 그리고 그들의 돈을
sort of get all of their money, like
전부 끌어모으면,
there's sort of no
실제로
one who can actually come in and do
다음 시리즈 A에 들어와서 투자할 수 있는 사람이
the next series A, and then basically you're
남지 않게 되고, 그러면 기본적으로 여러분은
safe. Like
안전해집니다. 그러니까
you have capital as a bludgeon is capital
자본을 곤봉처럼 휘두르는 것, 그 경우 자본은
as a moat in that case, right? So
그 경우 자본은 해자 역할을 합니다. 그래서
yeah, Harvey is interesting
네, Harvey는 흥미로운데
because, you know, uh, Lagora is coming fast
Lagora가 빠르게 그들을 추격하고 있고
for them. And obviously we have some skin
있기 때문입니다. 그리고 당연히 저희는 Lagora에 어느 정도 이해관계가
in the game
있지만
on Lagora, but we think that they have,
저희는 그들이,
uh, as good a shot at any, I
어, 누구 못지않게 가능성이 있다고 봅니다, 저는
guess that's one trend that we saw
제가 보기엔 저희가 본 한 가지 트렌드는
in 2025 is that there was like a
2025년에 본 트렌드 중 하나는
first wave of like AI hate of companies
AI 기업들에 대한 첫 번째 물결의 일종의 AI 혐오가
like Harvey.
Harvey 같은 회사들에 대한 첫 번째 물결의 일종의 AI 혐오였다는 것입니다.
Who might've wasted a lot of money on
실제로 파인튜닝에
fine tuning actually.
돈을 많이 낭비했을 수도 있습니다.
Totally. That like broke out really big in
맞습니다. 그게 2023년에
2023 and kind of did a victory lap
정말 크게 터졌고, 일종의 승리 선언을
that, you know,
했습니다. 그러니까,
oh, we've won the space. And now we're
"우리가 이 분야를 먹었다"라고 말한 것입니다. 그리고 이제는
seeing a second wave of companies like Lagora
Lagora 같은 회사들의 두 번째 물결과
and Giga.
Giga 같은 회사들을 보고 있습니다.
And it turns out that like, oh, actually
그리고 알고 보니, 그러니까, 사실
like it isn't so simple.
그게 그렇게 단순하지는 않다는 것입니다.
Yeah. The wood beneficiary of, um, you know,
네. 결국 수혜자는, 음, 그러니까,
burning some non-trivial double-digit percentage of
자본 구조의 적지 않은 두 자릿수 비율을
your capital stack on fine tuning that buys,
파인튜닝에 태워서 얻는 것은,
you know, advantage is like basically the investors
그러니까 그 ‘우위’의 수혜자는 사실상 투자자들이고
are the only winners there because they just
거기서 이기는 쪽은 그들뿐인 게,
own more of your company, you know?
결국 여러분 회사의 지분을 더 많이 갖게 되기 때문입니다, 그렇지요?
Yeah. So at least it relates to like
네. 그래서 적어도 이것은
the, the hiring and team size. I feel
채용과 팀 규모 문제와는 연결되는 것 같습니다.
like
그러니까
of the two camps, one being the AI
두 진영이 있는데, 하나는 AI가
is going to make everything more efficient. You
모든 것을 더 효율적으로 만들어서 여러분은
will need less
더 적은
people and the other AI is going to
사람만 필요해질 거라는 쪽이고, 다른 하나는 AI가
reduce the cost of like producing the time
뭔가를 만드는 데 걸리는 시간, 즉 생산 비용을
to produce things.
낮춰 줄 거라는 쪽입니다.
And so then the expectations from your users
그러면 사용자와
and customers will just go up and you'll
고객의 기대치가 계속 올라가고, 여러분은
need to
그래서
keep hiring more people to satisfy like the
그 늘어나는 기대를 충족하려고 더 많은 사람을
growing expectations.
계속 채용해야 하게 됩니다.
I feel like this year has been more
제 느낌엔 올해는 더
in that second camp. And I think that
그 두 번째 진영에 가까웠던 것 같습니다. 그리고 저는
is what's driving the fact
그게 이런 사실을 설명한다고 봅니다.
that the companies are still just hiring as
기업들이 여전히
many people as they were pre AI. It's
AI 이전과 비슷한 수준으로 계속 사람을 뽑고 있다는 점입니다. 다만
just like the bar
기준이, 그러니까
for what the software, what their customers expect.
소프트웨어에서 고객이 기대하는 수준의 문턱이 올라갔을 뿐입니다.
And they're all in the, you know, like
그리고 다들, 그러니까
Lagora's
Lagora는
racing with Harvey, Giga's racing with Sierra. Like
Harvey와 경쟁하고, Giga는 Sierra와 경쟁하듯이,
they're all still competing for the same set
모두가 여전히 같은 고객군을 놓고
of
서로
customers and they still ultimately are bottlenecked on
경쟁하고 있고, 결국 병목은 여전히
like people and like, I don't think anyone's
사람입니다. 저는 누구도
bottlenecked on ideas, but they're bottlenecked on like
아이디어 때문에 병목이 생긴다고는 생각하지 않지만, 정말 잘 실행할 수 있는
people who can execute really well.
사람 때문에 병목이 생깁니다.
I don't know. I think that's like, so
모르겠습니다. 제 생각엔 그래서
it's exciting. It feels like an exciting phase.
흥미롭습니다. 흥미로운 국면인 것 같습니다.
I agree with you that like the era
저도 동의합니다. 1명이
of the one person running a trillion dollar
1조 달러 규모의
company is not
회사를 운영하는 시대는
here. Not yet.
아직은 아닙니다. 아직은요.
Yeah. But I think it's going to trend
네. 하지만 결국 그쪽으로
that way eventually. That'll be a wild time.
흘러갈 거라고 생각합니다. 정말 엄청난 시기가 되겠지요.
Maybe that's
어쩌면 그게
a prediction for... For next year?
예측일 수도 있겠네요... 내년에 대해서요?
...2026. Yeah.
...2026년이요. 네.
Do you think it's coming?
그게 올 거라고 보십니까?
I mean, I don't think it'll happen in
그러니까 제 생각엔
2026 either, honestly. I mean, I think you
솔직히 2026년에도 일어나지는 않을 것 같습니다. 제 말은, 저는
will have
앞으로
many stories of companies run by, you know,
그러니까 100명 미만으로 운영되면서
under a hundred people that are making hundreds
수억 달러를 벌어들이는
of
기업들의
millions of dollars. Yeah.
많은 사례가 나올 거라고 생각합니다. 네.
So, I mean, Gamma was interesting to see.
그래서, 그러니까 Gamma가 흥미로웠습니다.
Like one of the biggest things that they
예를 들면 그들이
said in their launch
출시 때 말한 것들 중 가장 큰 것 하나가
that I think is a very good trend
제 생각엔 아주 좋은 트렌드였는데,
is they said they got to a hundred
그들이
million dollars in ARR with
ARR 1억 달러에
only 50 employees. So, which is very different.
직원 50명만으로 도달했다고 했습니다. 그래서, 그건 정말 다릅니다.
It's, you know, such an inversion, right? Like
그러니까 완전히 역전이죠, 그렇지요? 보통은
normally you have the big banner and the
큰 배너가 있고
like little X thing, you know, image. And
작은 X 같은 것, 그러니까 이미지가 있고, 그리고
it's like, oh yeah,
‘아, 맞아,’
like we raised all this money and look
‘우리가 이렇게 많은 돈을 모았고, 그리고’
at all the people who work for us.
‘우리 회사에 일하는 사람이 이렇게 많다’라고 하지요.
It's a good trend to have the reverse
그 반대로 자랑하는 흐름이 좋은데,
flex, which is like, look at all this
즉, ‘이 매출을 봐라, 그리고’
revenue and look how few
‘얼마나 적은 사람이 일하는지’를
people work for us. Well, that's all we
‘봐라’라는 겁니다. 자, 이번에는 여기까지입니다.
have time for this time. We just wanted
이번에는 시간이 여기까지였습니다. 저희는 그저
to wish you
여러분께
a really happy holidays and happy new year
즐거운 연말연시와 새해 복 많이 받으시길
from all of us to you and yours.
저희 모두를 대표해 여러분과 가족분들께 전해 드리고 싶었습니다.
See you next time.
다음에 또 뵙겠습니다.